hey what's up guys my name is vicherno
welcome back to my c plus plus series
today we're going to be talking all
about maps if you have been programming
for any amount of time really you
probably have heard of a map or a hash
map or a hash table or an associative
array basically these refer to a data
structure that allows you to associate
some kind of key with a value so for
example you have some sort of id such as
like an id number and you'd like to use
that to look up the rest of the data at
its core a map is kind of similar to an
array like a vector or a static array
even if you think back to a vector i've
made a video on that by the way i'll
have it linked up there a vector uses an
integer indexing system every element
that we push into that vector gets an id
which is its index inside that data
structure that works fine if you just
need like ascending indices 0 1 2 3 4 5.
if that means something to you then
again that works great or if you just
need to store like an array of elements
and you might care about the order of
those elements but you don't necessarily
care about accessing them randomly based
on some other value you just need to
have them like in a bucket so that
they're stored somewhere and you can
iterate through them that's where a
vector is really useful however if you
need to constantly retrieve specific
elements from that vector that's where
it can become a little bit of a problem
because to find a particular element if
you just have one piece of data and
you'd like to retrieve the entire
element means that you have to search
the entire vector sorting can help here
because if you sort it in some way then
maybe you can minimize how much of the
vector it has to search but you still
have to search the vector to find what
you're looking for that's basically a
problem that maps solve with a map you
can define a key which is like the thing
that you use to look up your value and
then of course a value which is the data
that you're looking for if you have that
key which could be like an id it could
be a name you can just retrieve the
value really easily because that key can
be used as an index like instead of an
integer in a vector it can be used as an
index to retrieve that data i know we're
only scratching the surface it's going
to be a long video buckle down but let's
dive in and take a look at a simple
example to begin with now when we're
talking about using maps in c plus plus
there are actually two different types
of maps and we are going to talk about
what they are today we have map and we
have unordered maps why are there two
different types of maps well because
they're different types of maps one of
them is a sorted map meaning that all of
the elements are actually ordered and
the other map on ordered map is
unordered so the ordered map which is
just called map is a self-balancing
binary search tree typically a red black
tree you don't really need to know the
details of that although we might get
into it in a future video but basically
all you need to know is it is a tree and
you typically find elements by comparing
them to other elements and seeing like
where a key falls
as you go through the branches and
because it's a tree like a binary tree
the elements end up being sorted because
they're kind of compared to each other
using a less than operator and stored in
the appropriate place that's why when
you iterate through an scd map you have
all of the elements in order in some
order now on the other hand unordered
map is a hash table it uses a hash
function to hash your key and it can use
that kind of generated index to figure
out which bucket your value lies in and
then that's how you retrieve your value
this is completely unordered and usually
can actually be quite a bit faster than
map but we will get into performance
later in this video because it's a bit
of a complicated topic as a basic rule
of thumb i would probably recommend that
you use unordered map wherever possible
unless you need an actual sorted data
structure because unordered map usually
ends up being faster than map or at the
very least the same speed okay let's
create our fictional scenario example
here let's say i have some kind of city
record that i want to maintain now
cities typically have like a name maybe
they have a population which can
apparently be above 4 billion they might
have some kind of like
latitude and longitude
anyway you get the point we have a city
we have data belonging to a city now
what i want to do is store every single
city that we have in the entire world so
i'm going to create a vector to
demonstrate this to begin with we're
going to have a vector of city record
these are going to be our cities
and then whenever i want to add a new
city here i can just like you know in
place back a city
provide a name so i live in melbourne so
let's use melbourne as an example
population like five million latitude
longitude i don't actually i'm
regretting even writing that but let's
just write this i'm gonna add a few more
cities we're gonna have
lol town
and let's add berlin let's add harris
and london and i'm just going to keep
all the rest of the data as is so now
that we have all of this data organized
nicely into a data structure what would
i need to do to retrieve information
about a specific city so let's say i
want to know the population of berlin
how would i find that out well with the
way that we've currently written this
we basically have to iterate through
like the entire cities vector and then
basically check to see if city dot name
equals whatever our
like the name that we're searching for
is such as berlin if it is then
fantastic we have our city and we can
easily look up the population this will
be the population of berlin done right
and of course we could break from this
for loop once we found it do whatever we
want with it that data is there can you
see the problem here
there's a few problems let's discuss
them first of all searching every single
city that we have is a bit of a pain now
it is true that we could maybe order
these alphabetically
and then use some kind of binary search
algorithm to kind of narrow down the
city that we're looking for we know it
starts with letter b so if we have an
ordered vector then of course you know
we could optimize that in some way
however if it is in fact completely
random and we have like a thousand or
ten thousand cities or something in here
then worst case scenario we have just
done ten thousand string comparisons
looking for berlin string comparisons
aren't exactly cheap either so basically
what i'm saying is using a vector for
this is not really ideal what i would do
instead is use a map so let's take a
look at how we would use just a normal
city map when we created it takes in two
template arguments well actually it can
take a lot more than two but for the
simple case you have to provide two it
takes in a key and it takes in a value
now the key is what you use to index
into your data so again since we are
indexing these by name we would use an
scd string as the key so let's type in
std string now the value is the data
that we're actually storing for that key
which of course will be a city record so
i'll call this city map how do we go
ahead and put all of these into the map
well
we basically can use something similar
but i'm going to change it up a little
bit into something that's a bit more
common and i'm just going to write
citymap equals city record like that and
we'll just replace these parentheses
with curly brackets and in here i
specify my key so let's go ahead and put
in melbourne
lol town
i don't know how we ended up with lol
town
considering all the other cities are
real but whatever and that's it so now
we've again we're associating a
particular key with that value in a
vector this would just end up being like
zero one two three blah blah but of
course here you can see we have an
actual meaningful key that is in fact a
string which is the name of the city so
now that we have this data structure how
do i retrieve information about berlin
well the good news is i just do it like
that so let's grab our city record out
of here berlin data and that's it and
again if i want my population
then i can just do billion
data.population there's my population
how easy was that and again it's not
just easy it's really fast for a small
data set like this it probably is about
the same speed but the larger your data
set is the faster this will essentially
be this has the added bonus of being
ordered so if i was to iterate through
all of these then these cities would
actually be in alphabetical order but no
you said an unordered map is faster
maybe how do you use an unordered map
well you'll be delighted to know that
it's the same but you just change the
type to unordered map the api is
identical all right that's pretty much
the video but you know me i'm gonna keep
talking for like another 20 minutes
probably so let's just get this over and
done with first actually before i
commence my monologue do you need web
hosting you probably do in some capacity
and for that i recommend that you use
hostinger the sponsor of today's video
hosinger is an amazing web hosting
platform that i personally use for all
of my websites and have for quite a
while the best thing about hostinger is
that it's extremely affordable but it
doesn't sacrifice quality their servers
are really reliable their user
interfaces are fantastic and they also
have a bunch of well-written
documentation and tutorials to help you
get started the process of setting up a
brand new server is you're watching it
right now it's really simple i probably
can't even finish this sentence in time
yeah there's like nothing more to say if
you need a web host then just go to
hosting that's hosting.com just make
sure that you use my channel coupon code
at checkout to get an even bigger
discount huge thank you to hosting as
always for sponsoring this video alright
so
maps let's dive in and take a look at
maps in much more detail most of what
i'm going to explain here applies to
both unordered map and map obviously the
specific stuff i will mention but as i
mentioned the api is very similar so
first of all let's discuss this in a bit
more detail so again we have a key
obviously an std string now it's really
important first and foremost that
whatever you use as the key
is actually hashable if you're using an
arnold map or it has less than operator
if you're using an scd map if we decided
that we actually wanted for example to
be like well let's create a map of city
record to
i don't know some additional data that
we wanted maybe that wasn't part of this
original struct such as like i don't
know the year that it was like founded
in or something like that if we tried to
create something like that so that we
could pass in a city record and then get
information about when the city was
founded as an example founded map then
if we try to compile this with control
f7 we're gonna get a crazy
like error message and i'm telling you
this is one of the worst things about
both c plus plus and maps if you don't
understand what the problem is you are
basically screwed like come on like are
we going to read this we could we could
show you guys how to read this this is
also why by the way i always recommend
that instead of looking at the error
list which just says
hey man this scd compare thing is
attempting to
uh reference a deleted function whatever
that means you look at the output
because if you look at the output then
you don't just get that error message
that this error list has passed you
actually get all of it which look how
much more detail it has this is all the
one error by the way so if you actually
follow this through you'll see that
eventually you get to message c
reference to class template
instantiation and if we double click on
this it will take us first of all to
where we are which as you can see is
that founded map that i tried to create
really important that you look at the
output now it's telling you here by the
way all of the template arguments so we
know that for example it's trying to use
scd-hash city record
that doesn't exist basically the reason
that we're getting this error is because
we're trying to use the hash function to
hash cityrecord we have to hash that key
so that we can you know store the value
and then retrieve the key again
everything goes through the hash
function as i mentioned but cityrecord
is a custom type so how is super
supposed to know how to hash this now as
a side note if this was for example a
city record pointer which again a lot of
people like to use and if you're coming
from a managed language then basically
everything is usually appointed there
that is a different story why because a
pointer is just an integer it's a 64-bit
integer on a 64-bit you know compiled
binary so it's obviously going to be
able to hash that because you may as
well have written a uint64t
right easily hashable the language comes
or the standard template library i
should say comes with that ability out
of the box now cityrecord on the other
hand without the pointer is no longer an
integer that actually is this data so it
doesn't know how to hash it so what do
we do well we have to provide
a hash function for city record now i'm
going to be honest with you guys this is
one of the things that i pretty much
google
anytime i have to implement because i
don't remember how to do this off the
top of my head but i have already worked
out how to do this for the purpose of
this video so i'll show you how to do it
but yeah program is google stuff all the
time and that's i mean that's pretty
obvious right now theoretically if we
wanted to we could kind of reverse
engineer this because we know that it's
it's basically going to come up to here
and try and use hash but it's like
again going through the senate template
libraries a bit of a nightmare so what
we basically have to do is create a
template specialization for the std hash
class that is specialized with the type
that is our key so normally we would
implement it like this namespace std
because this has to be in the city
namespace and then we're going to create
a template specialization for the hash
struct now this hash struct again
because it's a template specialization
we're going to type in template with an
empty template argument and then we're
going to specify the template argument
here so of course hash of city record is
what we'll be creating and then that
comes with an operator a parentheses
operator which is like the call operator
that returns a size t which is that hash
value a 64-bit uint and then we specify
a city record a const reference to a
city record as our like key that will be
hashing basically and then it's up to us
to return any kind of hash value that we
want now we could just return zero and
then obviously all city records are now
equal because whenever you hash a city
record you always get zero so we don't
want to do that instead we want to maybe
take a look at the data and be like what
uniquely identifies this now cities
don't really have unique names i mean
there are many cities in the world
especially if you don't just look at
like capital cities obviously but you go
further down
so you could like you know hash the name
with the population and combine that and
latitude and longitude latitude
longitude actually probably is a much
better way to go but as an example let's
take a look at name so how would we hash
name well name is a string so this is
obviously something that c plus already
has the ability to hash because s cd
string is part of the center template
library and the standard template
library includes hash functions for like
most of the types there so for this we
can just call hash with key dot name now
unfortunately it's not as
straightforward as that because hash is
a templated class here so we actually
have to put an sd string and
additionally we're actually calling this
operator so with that so we actually
have to basically
kind of like construct this and then
call it anyway syntax looks a bit weird
but this is what we can do so yeah looks
a bit weird but does the job so that is
something that you should
like copy and paste install i mean
whenever i need this honestly when i'm
working on a project like hazel i just
look elsewhere in the code base and copy
it from there because again i don't
retain this information but this is
basically how it works hopefully it
makes sense how it works you just put in
your custom type here the call operator
with that template specialization is
what kind of gives you an opportunity to
specify how that type should be hashed
and then whatever code you put into this
function is what generates a hopefully
unique hash for this specific object
again your goal here is to be unique
because you need to obviously if it's
not unique then you could type in
another city name and it could amount to
the same value which means that it will
overwrite data that's stored there
hopefully that makes sense anyway now if
we hit control f7 then this still
doesn't compile because if you read this
no overloaded function takes four
arguments so the reason this didn't
compile here is because
i i'm not sure why it just decided to
break now or maybe it never worked but
basically i used in place back with four
arguments here for the vector but we
don't technically speaking have a
constructor that matches that i was
hoping that it wouldn't matter but
anyway since we're past vectors if you
wanted to make this work obviously
within place back you would just write a
constructor that took in all those
arguments instead of kind of leaving up
to the struct initializer list but we
are going to just get rid of our
vector control f7
and there we go compiles and everything
is wonderful now so yeah our founded map
obviously works we can basically grab
like a city record such as this and push
into that like the year that it was
founded which i have no idea when melon
was founded but let's just say 1850. the
interesting thing about this is again
the only thing that identifies this is
the fact that it's a city record of
melbourne like this data could be
whatever like if i wanted to retrieve
you know the year a bit later
like so then i could specify whatever i
want here it doesn't matter because it's
just going to use this to look up my
value because that is obviously what the
hash function is using now this is a
fantastic time to mention what this
index operator actually does because
it works a little bit differently than
in other languages because this index
operator that you use to insert things
in we'll always insert things in there
is no const version of this operator
what am i talking about well let's get
rid of this founded map because it's a
little bit annoying
if i wanted to look up berlin like so if
berlin didn't actually exist
then this code here actually will insert
berlin into the unordered map
and then give me a reference to that
newly inserted city record
right and of course in this case we're
not specifying like parameters for it i
mean we're not specifying any values for
these variables so it will just be the
default value which will be like you
know an empty string and uninitialized
memory whatever this can be annoying if
you are new to c plus plus now i
personally use this all the time because
if there's a lot of data that needs to
be filled out here and i just want to
have access to that city record already
in the right place this is great because
i can then go through and do things like
billion
name you know equals billion right i can
go through and set up everything and
because it's a reference to that already
in place memory i don't need to then
later set it so like an alternative way
to do this might be let's create a brand
new city record by writing some code
like this
right let's set up like the name and the
population and like whatever else you
need to set up and then we can just
basically get our map
and assign that back in
like so now the downside here is that
you're creating it first here on this
kind of stack and then you're copying
that into the map whereas over here
apart from not having that final line of
code because it's not necessary you're
also avoiding the copy because you're
kind of creating it in place and then
referencing that memory so i actually
tend to use this quite a lot to just
avoid copies and to make the code a
little bit cleaner but if i really truly
want to retrieve the data without
actually inserting it then what i should
be using is dot at
now as a quick little note before i show
you dot at since this index operator
inserts elements if they're not there if
you happen to have like a const map so
if i
wrote something like const auto
cities equals city map so now i have a
const map right this map is now const if
i try to write code like this of course
it won't work because there is no const
version of this operator so if you pass
like a const map into a function you
have to use dot app
like i remember back in the day i was so
confused as to why i couldn't use index
operators
if the map was const i'm like but i'm
just trying to access because like in
java and c sharp whatever this is normal
right
but in c plus plus that operator is kind
of like it has the ability to mutate the
actual data of course the map because it
can insert elements so of course there
can't be a constant they could have made
a const version that would not insert
elements but i guess to keep it less
confusing they made dot at instead so
dot add is in fact const because it will
never insert new elements it will only
return those elements to you now of
course it will return them to you in a
const state which is why that wasn't
working and well for this example it's
not gonna work because we can't assign
to that obviously it's const so yeah my
rule of thumb is i use dot at everywhere
unless i
am okay with it inserting data which
again sometimes like on the fly you
don't mind if the element's not there
insert it sure that works for me but a
lot of the times you don't want that to
happen
now what happens if the data isn't there
so we don't have build in here so what's
going to happen here well you're going
to crash it's going to like throw an
exception or something or a set if you
use dot at the data has to be there so
how does one check to see if the data is
there that's where we can use dot find
and again it's pretty simple you can
just write cities dot find berlin which
is my key doesn't equal
cities dot end i don't know why my new
visual studio is decides to convert that
into that i guess that's just trendy
these days but anyway we'll ignore that
and then inside this if block you can
actually use dot app because you've
checked to make sure that it actually is
inside that map that pretty much covers
like a good deal of how to use map but
there is one other crucial part that you
might want to do and that is iterate
through the entire data structure so i
want to go through and print every
single city now lots of people will tell
you not to do this it's a bad idea it's
a map you don't integrate three maps
blah blah blah blah all that is false
ideally yes you wouldn't iterate through
maps because a vector keeps all of your
elements in contiguous memory very cache
friendly it's just it's the best thing
to do if you want to iterate through
elements that is why vectors in general
are by far like the most popular data
structure most of the time you use a
vector because it just stores all your
memory in a row and you probably don't
need fancy indexing systems like this
most of the time not saying maps are
unpopular they're extremely popular but
vectors are more popular however
iterating through maps is not the
slowest thing in the world it is slower
than a vector for sure if you iterate
through a vector it will always be
faster however it's also very useful to
be able to iterate through a map and
it's also very easy so all we have to do
if we want to iterate through our map
here is just write a for loop now i will
basically always write a for loop like
this for auto then reference if you
don't want to copy and then using
structured bindings in c 17 i can
actually just write like the name of my
key such as like the name of the city
and then whatever value i want so city
right because we have a name to city
record then i just specify my city map
so it's kind of like a range based for
loop here however we can use structured
bindings which by the way as i compile i
realize that we haven't enabled simple
17. let's just go over here we're on c
plus 14 apparently for some reason sure
17 is good enough you know what before
we do that let me just show you what you
would do like in c plus 14 again with
range based for lips and everything
what you can do is instead of iterating
through it and retrieving those the key
value immediately you can just uh make a
variable called like kv for key value
and then you have key value dot first
which is like your you know so let's
just do auto
name is that and then the city would be
your second so this is your city record
probably shouldn't use auto to be more
clear
and then that is your name now you can
see that in this case the key is
returned as a const value so we'll have
to do that as well because we can't
really edit it so this is like the stone
age of how you would iterate through a
map you don't really do that these days
instead with civil 17 and above we can
use structured bindings so you can
immediately just have your name
and your
city over here and then well yeah you're
done like this is this is my name string
and this is my city and i can access
like you know whatever data i want so
let's go ahead and actually just print
all the cities we'll actually run a
program for once today i'll go through
print the name of the city
and then maybe let's print the
population
city.population and that shall be the
end of that scdc get
f5 and you can see that i am printing
all of my data let's kind of you know
change some of these so that it's not
silly bring back berlin and there you go
you can see that we're able to access
obviously all the entries inside our map
now you will notice that of course they
are not in alphabetical order because we
are using an unordered map now if you
look at this it does happen to be in the
order that they were inserted in but
again that's definitely not guaranteed
so
just be careful with that an unordered
map is unordered so this would be a
perfect time to show you how we would
have an ordered map so of course if we
would just use an scd map instead of
that sc unordered map and that's really
all we have to do so now if i hit f5
then you can see that we now have all of
these in alphabetical order how do we
remove one of these from the map you ask
why we can simply do citymap.erase and
then whatever key we want to erase so
for example we don't want paris in here
we just citymap.erase paris and that's
it no more paris now finally the last
thing that i have to show you is if we
go back to using the founded cities that
we had
so founded
city founded or whatever it was so we
basically have
the city record be the key and then we
have some kind of value
we had to specify a hash function
obviously for the hashmap for the
unordered map but for the
map for the audit map we actually have
to specify something as well now one
complain when you actually just create a
new map here but when you try and use it
so if i try to actually like you know
insert a value into here such as like
let's just copy this pop that in like
that ctrl f7 once we compile it it will
tell us that there is no
binary less than operator right so again
it will it's a it's a self balancing
binary tree it will try and compare the
two nodes to each other to see which one
is less than the other one so that it
can sort it into the appropriate branch
that's not going to happen because there
is no less than operator so how do we
define a less than operator well you can
actually define one within your custom
class itself so obviously it's going to
return bull and we literally just need
to have a lesson operator so const city
record
other
we'll mark it as const
and then we can return true or false for
if it's less than something else so
let's sort these by population and this
is cool as well because you can sort it
by whatever you want because it has name
you know we don't have to sort it by
name although we could we could sort it
by population so we'll return population
less than other population as a quick
side note this lesson operator is
responsible for more than just sorting
of course this is what defines the
unique key inside your actual map so if
one city's population is the same as
another city's population they'll
actually clash so it's important that
you you know do this properly not just
for sorting let's compile it with ctrl
f7 again you can see it compiles now
before we add all of these into this
city founded map another interesting
note is because this index operator
inserts elements we can actually write a
bunch of statements like this without
even setting it equal to like you know
the year that it was founded in right
because this code itself will actually
insert the element in and that might be
all we're trying to do so that's also
something that people do from time to
time okay so we're iterating through our
city map over here let's go ahead and
insert all these cities into city
founded so we'll just do city founded
and then city and then i mean it doesn't
really matter when it was founded for
this example we'll just set it to that
and then what i want to do is
iterate through city founded and we
should see of course that it's sorted by
population so this will be city this
will be founded the name we can print
here we won't set this let's run this
program i'll just comment out this as
well so that's not confusing so now
where and again this is another great
example of like i just want to insert
something not necessarily set a value
but just insert the key and finally if
we iterate through all of these we
should see them in ascending order
from the lowest population to the
highest population as you can see here
all right that's pretty much it now what
i would like to talk about next is
performance between these maps because
performance is very important i'm a game
engine developer i care about
performance the short answer as i
mentioned you want to basically use scd
on ordered map whenever you can if you
do not care about the order unless
you've actually benchmarked profiled all
of that stuff and you can see that std
map is actually faster in some compilers
i have seen that a cd map is faster than
an ordered map and you also have to
realize that this very much depends on
how much data you have if you have 200
elements 500 elements a thousand
elements inside a map
you're probably not going to see a big
performance difference if you have a
million elements in your map and you're
doing lookups then the hashmap will be
much faster if you don't need that data
to be ordered now when iterating through
maps which of course isn't the most
ideal thing in the world map generally
performs better than unordered map
however it will be an order of magnitude
faster to iterate through a vector so if
you're going to be iterating a lot and
not really doing lookups very often you
should still use a vector but if you're
mostly doing lookups iterating maybe for
debugging or every now and then then of
course you should use a map preferably
an unordered map if you don't need it to
be ordered the long answer is i will
probably make a video talking about the
performance between these maps and show
some actual benchmarks if you want to
see that leave a comment below i hope
you guys enjoyed this video if you did
please don't forget to hit the like
button let me know what you want to see
next in the seat below series in the
comment section below and also if you
need web hosting check out hosting up
using my link in description below thank
you guys for watching i'll see you next
time goodbye
[Music]
you